<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Hansard>
<Preface>
<title>
	Thursday, 27 July 2017 - Volume 724 - New Zealand Parliament 
</title>
<link>https://www.parliament.nz/en/pb/hansard-debates/rhr/combined/HansD_20170727_20170727</link>
<date>THURSDAY, 27 JULY 2017</date>
</Preface>

<Debates>
<Debate>
<title>URGENT DEBATES DECLINED</title>
<subtitle>Human Rights Commission—Report on the Experiences of Disabled Children and Adults in State Care</subtitle>
<Speeches>
<Speech>
<by>Mr SPEAKER</by>
<time>20170727 15:00:57</time>
<SpeechContents>
<Content>
<type>Speech</type>
<name>Mr SPEAKER</name>
<text> I have received a letter from Poto Williams seeking to debate under Standing Order 389 the Human Rights Commission's report "Institutions are places of abuse": The experiences of disabled children and adults in State care. This is a particular case of recent occurrence. The report was released today. The purpose of an urgent debate is to hold the Government to account for an action for which it is responsible, Speaker's rulings 207/2. Several previous Speakers have ruled that the absence of an action on the part of the Government is not a particular case of recent occurrence and I refer members to Speakers' rulings 212/2. The Government has not yet responded to the release of the report. It may be that an urgent debate would be warranted if a new Government policy or action is subsequently announced. In the meantime I note that the House is holding the Estimates debate, which is an opportunity to debate the Government's future spending plans. The health and social development sectors have not yet been debated. The member may wish to use that opportunity to debate this matter—Speaker's ruling 215/1. The application today is therefore declined.</text>
</Content>
</SpeechContents>
</Speech>
</Speeches>
</Debate>
<Debate>
<title>ESTIMATES DEBATE</title>
<subtitle>In Committee</subtitle>
<Speeches>
<Speech>
<by>RINO TIRIKATENE (Labour—Te Tai Tonga)</by>
<time>20170727 15:02:39</time>
<SpeechContents>
<Content>
<type>Speech</type>
<name>RINO TIRIKATENE (Labour—Te Tai Tonga)</name>
<text> Just continuing on with my contribution regard Vote Customs, the New Zealand Customs Service, one of its key roles is to protect our borders and to keep our community and our country safe from illicit drugs and other harmful materials. To its credit the Customs Service last year it did: it seized 292 kilograms of methamphetamine, and 1.1 tonnes of precursor was seized by the Customs Service. So it is doing a good job in that area.</text>
</Content>
<Content>
<type>a</type>
<name>RINO TIRIKATENE (Labour—Te Tai Tonga)</name>
<text>If you look at the wider picture though, there is P epidemic in our country. It is seen through the countless cases of addictions and damaged families wreaking havoc up and down the country. So much so that my whanaunga Peeni Henare said that up in Te Tai Tokerau, Kaitaia has now got the name "Kaifryer" due to the amount of P that is flooding that community and promoting the illicit black market. When I asked this very question about how much P or its precursor are actually crossing by the border, i.e., Customs is missing at the border, I posed that question to the controller and her vast team of lawyers and policy analysts, and senior managers and the lot, and I was absolutely aghast at the answer, because they could not give an answer. They did not—and all I asked was for an estimate, an estimate of how much P, how much drugs are they missing at the border. They all looked at each other and they could not come up with an answer. They say "Oh, because it's impossible for us to know."</text>
</Content>
<Content>
<type>a</type>
<name>RINO TIRIKATENE (Labour—Te Tai Tonga)</name>
<text>Well, we know that there is an absolute proliferation of P through our health system, through the police. P addiction is the No. 1 reason why parents can no longer look after their children, who go to their grandparents. It is a huge problem across our society. So we are getting only half the picture from the Customs Service. It is great for it to try to laud how great it is with what it is intercepting at the border, but it is really what it is missing. That is really what counts when it comes to Estimates. We are dealing with an Estimates bill and it cannot even estimate the amount of drugs and P and precursor that it misses. I think that is an indictment on the Customs Service.</text>
</Content>
<Content>
<type>a</type>
<name>RINO TIRIKATENE (Labour—Te Tai Tonga)</name>
<text>But it is no surprise, really, because under this Government it is all about making the numbers look good. It is all about giving half the story. It is great for Government members to say "Oh yes, but we intercepted X amount at the border. It's going up every year.", but we cannot estimate actually what is out there in society at the moment, even though we know that there is a flood. There is a flood of P coming across the border. So much so that it is called the quiet tsunami. That is why this Government is failing. We have had 9 long years of it giving doctored numbers, giving us half the story, whether it is in the health system, whether it is in employment figures, whether it is in the P numbers themselves. [Bell rung] We are being disserved by this Government and we need to have a change, because we know we want to get the full picture.</text>
</Content>
</SpeechContents>
</Speech>
<Speech>
<by>The CHAIRPERSON (Hon Chester Borrows)</by>
<time>20170727 15:07:28</time>
<SpeechContents>
<Content>
<type>Speech</type>
<name>The CHAIRPERSON (Hon Chester Borrows)</name>
<text> Order! In this debate, when you get the bell, you sit down or you seek another call. I just remind members that in this debate, we are debating the report, so members should limit—</text>
</Content>
<Content>
<type>Interjection</type>
<name>Rino Tirikatene</name>
<text> I raise a point of order, Mr Chairperson.</text>
</Content>
<Content>
<type>ContinueSpeech</type>
<name>The CHAIRPERSON (Hon Chester Borrows)</name>
<text> Well, I am actually speaking at the moment, so you will have to wait. During the course of this debate, we are debating the report. So if members want to wax lyrical and jump into a campaign speech, they will be pulled up, as other speakers have been. Members are reminded that this is a debate on the report. </text>
</Content>
</SpeechContents>
</Speech>
<Speech>
<by>RINO TIRIKATENE (Labour—Te Tai Tonga)</by>
<time>20170727 15:08:05</time>
<SpeechContents>
<Content>
<type>Speech</type>
<name>RINO TIRIKATENE (Labour—Te Tai Tonga)</name>
<text> I raise a point of order, Mr Chairperson. I just want to draw your attention to the fact that the timer in the Chamber is all over the place. So if you could send a message to your Clerks that—</text>
</Content>
</SpeechContents>
</Speech>
<Speech>
<by>The CHAIRPERSON (Hon Chester Borrows)</by>
<time>20170727 15:08:18</time>
<SpeechContents>
<Content>
<type>Speech</type>
<name>The CHAIRPERSON (Hon Chester Borrows)</name>
<text> Well, by way of explanation, the timer was going up because you were told you had 3 minutes and 55 seconds. It is easier to calculate if we set the timer from zero going up, so that when it hits 3.55, we can press a button and make you sit down—albeit it has not been that effective in doing that—and now you will notice that the time will start from 5 minutes and count down to zero.</text>
</Content>
</SpeechContents>
</Speech>
</Speeches>
</Debate>
</Debates>
<Bills>
</Bills>
</Hansard>
