<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">

<meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="chris-bishop" href="#" showAs="CHRIS BISHOP (National)"/>
        <TLCPerson id="andrew-little" href="#" showAs="ANDREW LITTLE (Leader of the Opposition)"/>
        <TLCPerson id="rino-tirikatene" href="#" showAs="RINO TIRIKATENE (Labour-Te Tai Tonga)"/>
       <TLCPerson id="chester-borrows" href="#" showAs="The CHAIRPERSON (Hon Chester Borrows)"/>
        <TLCPerson id="carmel-sepuloni" href="#" showAs="Carmel Sepuloni"/>
        <TLCPerson id="clare-curran" href="#" showAs="Clare Curran"/>
        <TLCPerson id="ruth-dyson" href="#" showAs="Hon RUTH DYSON (Labour-Port Hills)"/>
        <TLCPerson id="mallard-trevor" href="#" showAs="The CHAIRPERSON (Hon Trevor Mallard)"/>
        <TLCPerson id="lindsay-tisch" href="#" showAs="The CHAIRPERSON (Lindsay Tisch)"/>
        <TLCPerson id="paula-bennett" href="#" showAs="Hon PAULA BENNETT (Minister of State Services)"/>
        <TLCPerson id="speaker-deputy" href="#" showAs="Mr Deputy Speaker"/>
        <TLCPerson id="richard-prosser" href="#" showAs="RICHARD PROSSER (NZ First)"/>
        <TLCPerson id="bill-english" href="#" showAs="Rt Hon BILL ENGLISH (Prime Minister)"/>
 
        <TLCPerson id="speaker" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.speaker" showAs="Speaker {?}"/>
      </references>

</meta>

<preface>
<docTitle>
	Wednesday, 26 July 2017 - Volume 724 - New Zealand Parliament 
</docTitle>
<docDate>WEDNESDAY, 26 JULY 2017</docDate>
<docAuthority>parliament.nz</docAuthority>
<legislature>51st Parliament</legislature>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.parliament.nz/en/pb/hansard-debates/rhr/combined/HansD_20170726_20170726"/>
</preface>

<debateBody>
<questions>
            <question alternativeTo="" as="" by="" class="" endTime="" evolvingId="" id="" lang="" period="" refersTo="" space="" startTime="" status="" style="" title="" to="">{1,1}</question>
            <answer alternativeTo="" as="" by="" class="" endTime="" evolvingId="" id="" lang="" period="" refersTo="" space="" startTime="" status="" style="" title="" to="">{1,1}</answer>
 
        </questions>
<speech by="#speaker">
<from>Mr SPEAKER</from>
<p> Honourable members, yesterday, Chris Hipkins asked that I consider the use of interim answers to written parliamentary questions. He was concerned that Ministers are giving interim answers to a wide range of written parliamentary questions and, potentially, deferring the obligation to provide an answer until after the Parliament is dissolved.</p>
<p>Interim replies should only be used in exceptional cases. Every endeavour must be made to provide a full reply within the period specified in Standing Orders. They are not to be used as a matter of course or just because a Minister has a large volume of questions to answer. Answering questions is a duty of office for Ministers and, if they give an interim reply, they are under an obligation to follow up with a full reply as soon as possible. A question is not regarded as being answered until the final response is received (SR 201/3,4,5). If an interim response is to be provided, the Minister should not routinely wait until the due date to provide it. Usually, it will be apparent to the Minister's office, when it receives a question, whether an interim reply will be required.</p>
<p>I would be concerned if Ministers ever used interim replies to avoid providing answers to questions. There is now only a short amount of time left to lodge written questions, since they may be only lodged up until the time the Parliament is dissolved. It is my expectation that written questions lodged 6 or more working days before the dissolution of this Parliament will receive a substantive reply unless doing so requires an exceptional amount of collation and research. If members feel that they have received an interim reply when it is not justified, they should raise it with the Minister immediately and, if still not satisfied, bring it to my attention.</p>
<p>I intend to circulate a copy of this ruling to all Ministers.</p>
</speech>

<speech by="#speaker">
<from>Mr SPEAKER</from>
<p> I have received a letter from the Hon Damien O'Connor seeking to debate under Standing Order 389 the discovery of the cattle disease Mycoplasma bovis in South Canterbury. This is a particular case of recent occurrence and there is ministerial responsibility for the response to the disease by the Ministry for Primary Industries (MPI). The test for whether a particular case requires the immediate attention of the House is a high one. The risk to our primary sector from animal disease is an important matter. This outbreak has been responded to by MPI and is limited in its scope at present. I am not convinced that this matter is urgent enough to warrant setting aside the business of the House today, therefore the application is declined.</p>
</speech>

<petitions>
<heading>FILMS, VIDEOS, AND PUBLICATIONS CLASSIFICATION (INTERIM RESTRICTION ORDERS) AMENDMENT BILL</heading>
<heading>In Committee</heading>
<speech by="#chris-bishop">
<from>CHRIS BISHOP (National)</from>
<p> So Part 1 of the Films, Videos, and Publications Classification (Interim Restriction Order Classification) Amendment Bill—a catchy title, as my colleague Maggie Barry said during the second reading of this bill—deals with the substantive amendments to the principal Act, which is, of course, the Films, Videos, and Publications Classification Act 1993. The Act been amended a couple of times—I think probably more than a couple of times—over the last 24 years since it was passed. It is probably an Act that is need of a bit more of a substantive review as we move into the internet age. But what this bill does is make a couple of very small but, I think, very useful changes to advance and improve freedom of expression in New Zealand.</p>
<p>In the first and second readings of this bill members in the House canvassed the issues around the book Into the River, which was the genesis for this bill, basically—the unfortunate events of 2015 around Into the River, the award-winning novel by Ted Dawe. What happened there—and I do not want to traverse again the potted history—</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#trevor-mallard">
<from>The CHAIRPERSON (Hon Trevor Mallard)</from>
<p> No, that would be irrelevant.</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#chris-bishop">
<from>CHRIS BISHOP (National)</from>
<p> —because it takes about 6 minutes to explain and, as the Chair is pointing out, it would be irrelevant. But I do want to draw the Committee's attention to the exact changes in Part 1 to try to remedy the situation, to try to make sure that does not happen again.</p>
<p>So what we have in clause 4 of Part 1 is the replacement of section 49 with a new and expanded new section 49, which will become section 49 of the Act, to basically expand the tool kit that the president of the board of review, and also the High Court, can use when considering interim restriction orders. Basically, what happened with Into the River was that Family First lodged an appeal—the second appeal, or the fourth time a body was going to classify the book Into the River. Family First lodged an appeal and used this little-known section of the Act we are talking about, which was the power for the president to order an interim restriction. What the president did in that situation was—they did decide to do that and, of course, we had the effect of the book not being available for 6 weeks before the board of review met. Basically, the president was placed in that position because of the binary nature of interim restrictions.</p>
<p>So what new section 49 in clause 4 of this bill does is expand the tool kit. In particular, I am talking about subsection (3), which allows—sorry, it is subsection (3)(d), or (b). It allows—I will start that again. Section 49, subsection (3), paragraph (b)—</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#trevor-mallard">
<from>The CHAIRPERSON (Hon Trevor Mallard)</from>
<p> Clause 4.</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#chris-bishop">
<from>CHRIS BISHOP (National)</from>
<p> No, no, paragraph—the Chair is pointing out that I mean clause 4, but I actually mean subsection (3)(b), which allows the president to issue an interim restriction order that is more appropriately calibrated to the specific harm that may or may not be, in the opinion of the president, occurring as a result of this order. So what it does is it allows the president to issue an order that is more closely calibrated to the specific harm.</p>
<p>In the case of Into the River, which had been at various points classified R18 or R14, rather than simply saying that this publication is objectionable pending further appeal, they could say, I suppose, "It is partially objectionable but we will maintain it to be available for people over the age of 18.", or in the case—as you sometimes see going into things like the incredible film festival in Wellington in the early 2000s, you could also say it is available for film festival viewings or for tertiary study. I have a sort of objection in principle to the idea of restricting speech based on the fact that people are in tertiary education, or saying that a higher class of people go to film festivals. I tend to think that is a bit ridiculous, actually. But, regardless, that is in the Act, and that power, I suppose, to restrict to a specific audience is in the Act.</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#clare-curran">
<from>Clare Curran</from>
<p> I can feel another member's bill coming on.</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#chris-bishop">
<from>CHRIS BISHOP</from>
<p> So I am not going to traverse that. I did not hear that interjection, but—</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#clare-curran">
<from>Clare Curran</from>
<p> That's your next member's bill.</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#chris-bishop">
<from>CHRIS BISHOP (National)</from>
<p> Oh, that is my next member's bill, says Clare Curran. Well, possibly—I mean, this Parliament has got only a short run of life left in it, but you never know. My next member's bill is actually around celebrancy. I might get the third luck of the ballot on that one, but I highly doubt it—I do not think we can have another member's day.</p>
<p>So, anyway, that is the substantive amendment advanced through new section 49. Then, of course, we come to clause 5 of the bill—[Bell rung] Mr Chair.</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#trevor-mallard">
<from>The CHAIRPERSON (Hon Trevor Mallard)</from>
<p> I will call the member again, but I will remind him that we are discussing three clauses: clauses 4, 5, and 6. The member might be talking about a section of another Act, and if that is the case—he is a lawyer. He should know.</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#chris-bishop">
<from>CHRIS BISHOP (National)</from>
<p> Thank you, Mr Chair. We come to clause 5, which deals with similar powers to do with interim restrictions to do with the High Court. It is a little-known section about the power to do with interim restrictions in that they can also be appealed to the High Court. What the bill does is, essentially, replicate the same powers as in clause 4 of the bill in new section 67 in clause 5 in relation to the High Court, and that is just a consequential change that has to be replicated in the appeals to the High Court as a result of the changes we are making in clause 4 to section 49 of the Act.</p>
<p>Clause 6 inserts new section 133A. Again, this is a change that is necessary in response to the changes we are making through clause 4, which is about the potential penalties for people who contravene an interim restriction order. What the bill proposes as a result of the changes made by the very hard-working Justice and Electoral Committee is in subsection (3), which will make people liable to conviction or a fine not exceeding $3,000 or, in the case of a body corporate, $10,000. We had a bit of debate in the select committee, I think it is fair to say, about the level of fines. You could probably argue they should be greater, but we have decided to go for the moderate option that is put forward in the bill. So, with those brief introductory remarks, I will leave it there.</p>
</speech>
</petitions>

<petitions>
<heading>PRIVATE INTERNATIONAL LAW (CHOICE OF LAW IN TORT) BILL</heading>
<heading>In Committee</heading>
<speech by="#lindsay-tisch">
<from>The CHAIRPERSON (Lindsay Tisch)</from>
<p> This is debate on clauses 3 to 4, and schedule 1.</p>
</speech>
</petitions>

<petitions>
<heading>HEALTHY HOMES GUARANTEE BILL (NO 2)</heading>
<heading>Second Reading</heading>
<speech by="#andrew-little">
<from>ANDREW LITTLE (Leader of the Opposition)</from>
<p> I move, That the Healthy Homes Guarantee Bill (No 2) be now read a second time. This is, as members on this side of the House will know, a very important bill. It is, at the very least, symbolic about the very important challenges that New Zealand faces today. On this bill, the Government Administration Committee received 85 submissions, but there have been expressions of support from a large number of people from a number of other quarters as well.</p>
<p>The submissions that the select committee received came from organisations and private individuals from the length and breadth of the country. I would like to thank all those who made submissions on the bill and those who made oral submissions, in particular, and brought their very compelling reasons for support for the bill.</p>
<p>There were many private individuals who took the time to support it, to express their support for it, and to make their valuable comments. The district health boards, the New Zealand Medical Association, and other medical associations have provided expert support for the bill. And I especially want to mention the Paediatric Society of New Zealand for the invaluable data that it included in its exhaustive The Health Status of Children and Young People in New Zealand. Strong support has been provided by local government, social agencies, church groups, and iwi trusts, and then, of course, those very determined campaigners for social justice and the ending of poverty: the Child Poverty Action Group, Community Housing Aotearoa, Housing Call to Action, and the Tenants Protection Association.</p>
<p>Yesterday, the Medical Students for Global Awareness, along with other medical professionals who are strong supporters of the bill, presented me with their expression of support. It was a petition from medical professionals with no fewer than a thousand signatures on it. A public petition supporting the bill, which I tabled today, attracted more than 30,000 signatures.</p>
<p>This is a bill whose time has come, and for which the issues in it need to be seriously addressed. This bill has wide support because the reality is that we have a housing crisis in New Zealand today. And we all know the dimensions of it. We have the worst homelessness rate in the OECD. The Government is today spending $50 million a year shunting homeless families from one motel to another. That budget has blown out by 1,500 percent. The Government is spending 25 times more than it budgeted, and the situation is spiralling out of control.</p>
<p>This bill will help thousands of people. It will change lives and it will save lives. There is a very simple principle behind this bill: no New Zealander should have to live in a house that makes them or their children sick. Every Kiwi child deserves to grow up in a house that is warm, safe, and dry. As a parent, I would not accept anything less for my son; I do not think there is a New Zealand parent who would accept anything less for their children, and this Parliament should not accept anything less for any citizen of New Zealand.</p>
<p>The Children's Commissioner tells us that 42,000 children a year are turning up to the emergency departments in our hospitals with preventable respiratory conditions. This is what we are trying to fix. That number is intolerable, it is wrong, it can be fixed, and this bill can fix it.</p>
<p>Every rental property should be insulated, should be weathertight, and should have adequate heating. It is not too much to ask. You see, it is not just a problem for the poor. It is any tenant—anybody in a rental property. And here is the thing: there are thousands of landlords who are doing the right thing already and who know that it is the right thing to do as a landlord. We have got a housing crisis that is locking middle New Zealand and families out of homeownership, and that is why what this bill says is so important. It is about getting it right for those who have to rent. This bill is about standing up for those New Zealanders who have to rent.</p>
<p>And so the challenge for the Government is this—and we will see what way it votes tonight. The simple question for the Government is this: whose side is it on? Is it on the side of the slum landlords who do not care about their tenants—push them in, pull them out, put a new one in, and collect the rent—or is it on the side of New Zealanders who have a reasonable expectation that the place they end up renting is going to be safe and healthy for them to do so?</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#carmel-sepuloni">
<from>Carmel Sepuloni</from>
<p> Whose side are they on?</p>
</speech>
<speech by="#andrew-little">
<from>ANDREW LITTLE (Leader of the Opposition)</from>
<p> And that will be the challenge tonight. Whose side is the Government on?</p>
<p>You see, responsible landlords are telling us that this is a good bill. It will not impose big costs. When you look at the asset that this is about—a house, a private dwelling, a residential dwelling—and the life of that asset, the costs that this bill will impose on those who have not got their properties up to standard yet will be negligible. But they will be costs that will make a difference—make a difference for children, make a difference for adult tenants, and help to save lives.</p>
<p>Andrew King, from the New Zealand Property Investors Federation, called the bill sensible and pragmatic. And, as I said, most landlords are already doing this, because the cost is not high. So the question remains for the National: whose side is it on? You see, Nick Smith hides behind the excuse that we cannot insulate homes fast enough. He says this will impose extra cost, but the landlords are telling us this is a reasonable cost to bear if you have not already done the work. You see, the Children's Commissioner is calling National's response to the situation shameful and a broken promise. So whose side is it going to be on tonight? Making rentals warm and dry is doable, affordable, and it is the right thing to do.</p>
<p>The select committee considered a number of amendments to this bill, and they are all worthy amendments: making the bill consistent with the Government's smoke alarm requirements; increasing the transition time for landlords to comply—so compliance within 90 days of the new regulations coming into effect—giving landlords the right to enter a property on at least 24 hours' notice to make sure things are in order; requiring the Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment to create an inspection regime to audit rental properties; specifying more detail on indoor temperatures, moisture, and humidity standards; and increasing the penalty for failure to meet the standards, from $3,000 to $4,000.</p>
<p>As I said before, this bill can make a real difference for thousands of Kiwis. I am very grateful for the support that I have had on this bill, from the many thousands of New Zealanders who have expressed their support and from the many members of this House. I want to particularly thank Peter Dunne from United Future, who has tonight expressed his continuing support for this bill because he knows that this is the right thing to do.</p>
<p>No Government should side with slum landlords in this country. No Government should put the interests of slum landlords over the interests of Kiwi kids. This is a bill that can help Kiwi kids who, at the moment, are in vulnerable, unsafe, unhealthy homes and stop them having to turn up to hospital with their preventable respiratory conditions.</p>
<p>We are in this Parliament to make a difference. We are all in this Parliament to act in the best interests of all New Zealanders, and this is a small, modest, reasonable step that can be taken that ought to make every member of Parliament supporting the bill proud to do so. I urge all MPs—and I urge my colleagues opposite—to do the right thing. Back those New Zealand families who have to rent and back their kids and stop them getting sick any more. It is with great pleasure that I commend the Healthy Homes Guarantee Bill (No 2) to the House.</p>
</speech>
</petitions>

<petitions>
<heading>RATES REBATE (RETIREMENT VILLAGE RESIDENTS) AMENDMENT BILL</heading>
<heading>Second Reading</heading>
<speech by="#ruth-dyson">
<from>Hon RUTH DYSON (Labour—Port Hills)</from>
<p> I move, That the Rates Rebate (Retirement Village Residents) Amendment Bill be now read a second time. Early in the 1970s a great Prime Minister, Norman Kirk, looked at the situation that low-income earners found themselves in after they purchased a house and were, obviously, faced with an annual rates bill, which, for people then and now, is big. There is no way of avoiding it—it is not an option. You cannot say: "Oh, I'll do without the rates so I won't pay my rates." It is not like food or clothes or travel; you have to pay it. So he decided to introduce a rates rebate scheme—that was central Government money that was passed through to homeowners via local government. It was on a sliding scale, so the higher your rates and the lower your income, the more money you got. It is a very straightforward scheme based on an important principle: that people on low incomes who have high expenses not of their choosing deserve some financial support.</p>
<p>In those days, there was no such thing as licence to occupy; there was just freehold title or leasehold title. There was no such thing as licence to occupy. In fact, even now, within retirement villages—which are what this bill seeks to address—there is a mix of freehold title, unit title, and licence to occupy. This bill wants to extend the eligibility for application for rates rebate to those in retirement villages who have a licence to occupy. Those people pay rates. They pay them to the retirement village owner, and the retirement village owner then passes them over to the city council or district council.</p>
<p>The owners of villages support this legislation because they know it would advantage their residents. The retirement village residents support this because, again, they know it will advantage the residents who find it difficult—if they are solely dependent on superannuation, particularly—to pay their rates bill. It is exactly the same situation that Norman Kirk saw in the 1970s that we are facing now, it is just that the nature of the relationship between the person who lives in the unit in the retirement village and the village owner has changed. We no longer have as many unit titles.</p>
<p>I had an email from a woman today who lives in a retirement village in Mosgiel. She said, "I really hope your bill gets passed, because when I bought my unit in the retirement village I had no option but to buy under a licence to occupy regime."—so you pay a big deposit and then you pay ongoing fees. You have a licence to occupy; you do not have ownership. But she said that people who were also in exactly the same village, in exactly the same type of unit, had purchased 20 years ago and have got a unit title. They get a rates rebate; she does not. She thinks that is not fair, and I do not think it is fair either. I think she should get a rates rebate.</p>
<p>When I introduced this bill to the House and explained it in that way, every single member of this Parliament supported the bill to go to the Local Government and Environment Committee. I was delighted. It is not very often that happens. It is not very often that legislation is passed without exception. It is not very often that I agree with David Seymour, actually, but on this occasion I am delighted that he and I agree. The bill went to the select committee, and the submissions that we got were thoughtful and helpful. A lot proposed amendments; a lot said to make sure that this system works as efficiently as the rates rebate does for homeowners. The Retirement Villages Association, the organisation that represents the owners of retirement villages, came along very early and put its hand up and said: "We can help make this work for the owners. We can help make this work." Local Government New Zealand came along and put its hand up: "We can make this work." The Residents Association said: "We can make this work. We can help make it work efficiently." Everyone is onside.</p>
<p>The committee asked for an extension of 2 months. I did not think they needed it. It is a small bill; it does something very straightforward. There is no complexity about this, actually. Anyone who thinks this is complex is simple. I granted the 2 months' extension when the Hon Scott Simpson—who was not honourable at that stage but has since been appointed to the executive. I granted the 2 months' extension, and in that time the select committee did nothing—did nothing—to engage with those three organisations that had come along and put their hands up, saying: "We'll help make this work."</p>
<p>I went to the last deliberation of the select committee, and the chairperson of the select committee—it would have made you laugh if it had not been such an important issue for so many of our senior citizen residents—said this is a complex issue. No it is not; it is extending the rates rebate to people in a licence to occupy—no complexity about it. He said there will be some other forms of homeownership other than what is already covered by the rates rebate and what this extends to, so there will be another anomaly. Good—introduce a member's bill, Mr Bayly, and fix that, if you can find one, but you know you cannot. If you can find another anomaly, introduce a member's bill and fix it.</p>
<p>Then they said this could cost money. Well, that is rocket science, is it not? That is very good. The members of that committee may not know that every year there is an appropriation in the Budget for rates rebate, and not one year since 1973 when it was introduced has that full appropriation been used, so there is money in the bank sitting there ready to be spent. I think residents of retirement villages should be the recipients of that money.</p>
<p>Then the chairman, Mr Bayly, said: "Oh, this is going to be so difficult for councils to administer." You know, Auckland Council does it now. To be honest, and I do not want to offend Aucklanders—oh, yes, there are a few Aucklanders; actually, I am surrounded by Aucklanders, I will make no comment. Auckland Council administers a rates rebate scheme for residents of retirement villages who have a licence to occupy. It does it. It thought it was fair, but it uses ratepayers' money, not taxpayers' money. Kāpitī does it; other councils are looking at doing the same thing, because they think it is fair.</p>
<p>So having gone through a great process at the first reading and gone through what I think was a very engaged and—receiving offers of help from organisations that know this stuff far better than any members of Parliament; the Retirement Villages Association, the Retirement Village Residents Association of New Zealand, and Local Government New Zealand, all offering help. The National Government then says: "Oh, what a good idea, but we're not going to support it." It is the second example of petty party politics getting in the way of just doing some good for people who deserve support.</p>
<p>Those people in Mosgiel, in the retirement village, they will be listening to this debate. They know that five units down from them on the same street there is somebody getting a rates rebate because they bought over 20 years ago and have a unit title, and they are not getting a rates rebate because they did not plan ahead well enough. They should have bought long before they needed to so they did not end up with a licence to occupy.</p>
<p>It is stupid, but it is not stupid deliberately; it is stupid because our legislation did not keep up with the changing nature of occupancy in retirement villages. They are expanding, we know. Every time you turn around there is another retirement village. We should take this opportunity to support legislation that will give additional financial support to those who meet the criteria and are eligible for a rates rebate. It is a very small measure, but I think it would be something good that we could progress before the election for the benefit of those people. Rates bills are big. If you are on superannuation, they are really big. This is the chance for us to help those people.</p>
<p>Before I finish, I want to acknowledge those organisations that I said came along to offer their help. I also want to offer my thanks to Grey Power New Zealand branches all over the country, which have debated this bill and totally support it. It is a good measure. We are not going to get to vote on it tonight because we do not have enough time for 12 speeches, but we have got another member's day before we rise for the election, and we have other members' days after that. I certainly know that this bill will be continued. It is time the rates rebate—such a visionary idea for Norman Kirk—was extended to people who are eligible for it but not eligible to apply because they are in a licence to occupy. It is time to address that anomaly.</p>
</speech>
</petitions>

</debateBody>

    
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>

