<?xml version="1.0"?>
<akomaNtoso>
  <debate name="hansard">
    <meta>
      <references source="#source">
        <TLCOrganization id="source" href="/ontology/organization/ca.open.north.inc" showAs="Open North Inc."/>
        <TLCPerson id="bishop-chris" href="#" showAs="CHRIS BISHOP (National)"/>
        <TLCPerson id="borrows-chester" href="#" showAs="Hon Chester Borrows"/>
        <TLCPerson id="carter-david" href="#" showAs="David Carter (Speaker)"/>
        <TLCPerson id="curran-clare" href="#" showAs="CLARE CURRAN (Labour)"/>
        <TLCPerson id="mallard-trevor" href="#" showAs="Hon Trevor Mallard"/>
        
        <TLCPerson id="speaker" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.speaker" showAs="Speaker {?}"/>
        <TLCPerson id="deputy-speaker" href="#deputy-speaker" showAs="Deputy Speaker {?}"/>
        <TLCPerson id="chairperson" href="/ontology/person/ca-ns.chairperson" showAs="The CHAIRPERSON"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    
     <preface>
      <docTitle>Debates, Wednesday, 26 July 2017 - Volume 724</docTitle>
      <docNumber>724</docNumber>
      <docDate date="2017-07-26">Wednesday, 26 July 2017</docDate>
      <docAuthority>parliament.nz</docAuthority>
      <legislature value="51">51st Parliament</legislature>
      <session value="1">1st Session?</session>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.parliament.nz/en/pb/hansard-debates/rhr/combined/HansD_20170726_20170726"/>
    </preface>
    
    <debateBody>
      <prayers></prayers>
      
      <questions>
       <question alternativeTo="" as="" by="" class="" endTime="" evolvingId="" id="" lang="" period="" refersTo="" space="" startTime="" status="" style="" title="" to="">{1,1}</question>
       <answer alternativeTo="" as="" by="" class="" endTime="" evolvingId="" id="" lang="" period="" refersTo="" space="" startTime="" status="" style="" title="" to="">{1,1}</answer>
 
      </questions>
    
      <!-- https://www.parliament.nz/en/pb/hansard-debates/rhr/combined/HansD_20170726_20170726/tab/video?page=7&mode=form -->
      <!-- https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nwTd6RvvDoQ -->
      <!-- Speaker's Ruling -->
      
      <heading>Speaker's Ruling</heading>
      <speech by="#carter-david" as="#speaker" startTime="2017-07-26T14:01:56.000+12:00" status="undefined">
        <from>Mr SPEAKER</from>
        <p>Honourable members, yesterday, Chris Hipkins asked that I consider the use of interim answers to written parliamentary questions. He was concerned that Ministers are giving interim answers to a wide range of written parliamentary questions and, potentially, deferring the obligation to provide an answer until after the Parliament is dissolved.</p>

        <p>Interim replies should only be used in exceptional cases. Every endeavour must be made to provide a full reply within the period specified in Standing Orders. They are not to be used as a matter of course or just because a Minister has a large volume of questions to answer. Answering questions is a duty of office for Ministers and, if they give an interim reply, they are under an obligation to follow up with a full reply as soon as possible. A question is not regarded as being answered until the final response is received (SR 201/3,4,5). If an interim response is to be provided, the Minister should not routinely wait until the due date to provide it. Usually, it will be apparent to the Minister's office, when it receives a question, whether an interim reply will be required.</p>

        <p>I would be concerned if Ministers ever used interim replies to avoid providing answers to questions. There is now only a short amount of time left to lodge written questions, since they may be only lodged up until the time the Parliament is dissolved. It is my expectation that written questions lodged 6 or more working days before the dissolution of this Parliament will receive a substantive reply unless doing so requires an exceptional amount of collation and research. If members feel that they have received an interim reply when it is not justified, they should raise it with the Minister immediately and, if still not satisfied, bring it to my attention.</p>

        <p>We will begin the daily routine.</p>
      </speech>

      <petitions>
        <heading>FILMS, VIDEOS, AND PUBLICATIONS CLASSIFICATION (INTERIM RESTRICTION ORDERS) AMENDMENT BILL</heading>
        <heading>In Committee</heading>
        <heading>Part 1 Substantive amendments to principal Act</heading>

        <speech by="#bishop-chris" startTime="2016-07-27T16:05:46.000+12:00">
         <a name="time_20170726 16:05:46"></a>
         <from>CHRIS BISHOP (National)</from>
         <p>So Part 1 of the Films, Videos, and Publications Classification (Interim Restriction Order Classification) Amendment Bill—a catchy title, as my colleague Maggie Barry said during the second reading of this bill—deals with the substantive amendments to the principal Act, which is, of course, the Films, Videos, and Publications Classification Act 1993. The Act been amended a couple of times—I think probably more than a couple of times—over the last 24 years since it was passed. It is probably an Act that is need of a bit more of a substantive review as we move into the internet age. But what this bill does is make a couple of very small but, I think, very useful changes to advance and improve freedom of expression in New Zealand.</p>

        <p>In the first and second readings of this bill members in the House canvassed the issues around the book <em>Into the River</em>, which was the genesis for this bill, basically—the unfortunate events of 2015 around <em>Into the River</em>, the award-winning novel by Ted Dawe. What happened there—and I do not want to traverse again the potted history—</p>
</speech>
        <speech by="#mallard-trevor" as="#chairperson" status="undefined">
          <from>The CHAIRPERSON (Hon Trevor Mallard)</from>
          <p>No, that would be irrelevant.</p>
        </speech>
      </petitions>
 
    </debateBody>
    
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
